For years I've been feeling frustrated,
لسنوات كنت أشعر بالإحباط
because as a religious historian,
لأنني كمؤرخة للأديان،
I've become acutely aware
لقد أصبحت مدركة تماماً
of the centrality of compassion
للدور المركزي للتراحم
in all the major world faiths.
في كل المعتقدات الكبيرة في العالم .
Every single one of them
كل واحد منها
has evolved their own version
تطور بمفهومه الخاص
of what's been called the Golden Rule.
لما جرى تسميته بالقاعدة الذهبية.
Sometimes it comes in a positive version --
بعض الأحيان يأتي بمفهوم إيجابي --
"Always treat all others as you'd like to be treated yourself."
" دائماً عامل الآخرين بما تريدهم أن يعاملوك به."
And equally important
وبنفس القدر من الأهمية
is the negative version --
المفهوم السلبي --
"Don't do to others what you would not like them to do to you."
" لا تفعل للآخرين ما لا تريدهم أن يفعلوه لك."
Look into your own heart,
أنظر الى قلبك.
discover what it is that gives you pain
أكتشف ما يسبب لك الألم.
and then refuse, under any circumstance whatsoever,
ومن ثم أرفض،تحت اي ظرف
to inflict that pain on anybody else.
تسبيب ذلك الألم لأي شخص آخر.
And people have emphasized the importance of compassion,
وقد شدد الناس على أهمية التراحم،
not just because it sounds good,
ليس فقط لأنه يبدو جيداً،
but because it works.
بل لأنه ناجح.
People have found that when they have
أكتشف الناس أنهم حينما
implemented the Golden Rule
يطبقون القاعدة الذهبية
as Confucius said, "all day and every day,"
مثل ما قال كونفوشس، " طوال اليوم وكل يوم،"
not just a question of doing your good deed for the day
وليس مجرد مسألة أن تعمل الخير لليوم
and then returning to a life of greed
ثم تعود لحياة الجشع
and egotism,
والأنانية.
but to do it all day and every day,
لكن لنفعل ذلك طوال اليوم وكل يوم،
you dethrone yourself from the center of your world,
وأحرم نفسك من التمركز حول ذاتك،
put another there, and you transcend yourself.
ضع غيرك في مركز الاهتمام، وأسمو بنفسك.
And it brings you into the presence
وسيوصلك ذلك الى
of what's been called God, Nirvana, Rama, Tao.
الرب، ونيرفانا، وراما، وتاو.
Something that goes beyond
وهو ما يتجاوز
what we know in our ego-bound existence.
ما يُعرف بالأنانية لدينا.
But you know you'd never know it a lot of the time,
لكن تعرف أنك لا تعلم هذا في كثير من الأوقات،
that this was so central to the religious life.
أن ذلك كان مركزياً في الحياة الدينية.
Because with a few wonderful exceptions,
لأنه مع وجود إستثناءات قليلة رائعة،
very often when religious people come together,
في كثير من الأحيان عندما يلتقي المتدينون،
religious leaders come together, they're arguing about abstruse doctrines
حينما يجمع علماء الدين سوياً، فأنهم يتجادلون حول المذاهب الصعبة
or uttering a council of hatred
أو تأسيس مفوضية ضد الكراهية
or inveighing against homosexuality or something of that sort.
أو الإحتجاج ضد المثلية الجنسية أو شئ من هذا القبيل.
Often people don't really want to be compassionate.
في العادة لا يود الناس حقيقة أن يكونوا رحماء.
I sometimes see
أرى في بعض الأحيان
when I'm speaking to a congregation of religious people
عندما أتحدث مجموعة من المتدينين
a sort of mutinous expression crossing their faces
نوع من التعابير الغاضبة تعبر وجوههم
because people often want to be right instead.
لأن الناس دائماً يريدون أن يكونوا على حق.
And that of course defeats the object of the exercise.
وذلك بالطبع يهزم الغاية من هذا الدرس.
Now why was I so grateful to TED?
الآن، لماذا أنا ممتنة ل تيد؟
Because they took me very gently
لأنهم أخذوني بلطف شديد
from my book-lined study
من جانب دراساتي المغمورة
and brought me into the 21st century,
وقدموني للقرن الحادي والعشرين،
enabling me to speak to a much, much wider audience
أتاحوا لي فرصة الحديث مع جمهور أوسع بكثير
than I could have ever conceived.
مما كنت قد تصورته في أي وقت مضى.
Because I feel an urgency about this.
لأنني أشعر بضرورة ملحة حول هذا الأمر.
If we don't manage to implement
اذا لم نخطط لتطبيق
the Golden Rule globally,
القاعدة الذهبية عالمياً،
so that we treat all peoples, wherever and whoever they may be,
بحيث نعامل جميع الشعوب، في أي مكان وأياً كان،
as though they were as important as ourselves,
كما لو كانوا لا يقلون أهمية عن أنفسنا،
I doubt that we'll have
أشك في أننا سنحصل
a viable world to hand on to the next generation.
على عالم يمكن تسليمه للجيل القادم.
The task of our time,
مهمة عصرنا،
one of the great tasks of our time,
أحد المهام العظيمة لحقبتنا،
is to build a global society, as I said,
هي بناء مجتمع عالمي، كما قلت،
where people can live together in peace.
حيث يستطيع الناس العيش معاً بسلام.
And the religions that should be making a major contribution
و كل الديانات، يجب أن تسهم في ذلك
are instead seen as part of the problem.
بدلاً عن رؤيتها كجزء من المشكلة.
And of course it's not just religious people who believe in the Golden Rule.
وبطبيعة الحال ليست المتدينون فقط هم الذين يؤمنون بالقاعدة الذهبية.
This is the source of all morality,
هذا هو مصدر كل الأخلاقيات.
this imaginative act of empathy,
الفعل الخيالي للعاطفة،
putting yourself in the place of another.
تضع نفسك في مكان الآخر.
And so we have a choice, it seems to me.
وبهذا يكون لدينا الخيار، كما يبدو لي.
We can either go on bringing out or emphasizing
يمكننا إما المضي في إبراز، أو التركيز
the dogmatic and intolerant aspects of our faith,
على جوانب التحجّر وعدم التسامح في معتقادتنا،
or we can go back to
أو يمكننا العودة الى
the rabbis. Rabbi Hillel, the older contemporary of Jesus,
الحاخامات ، الحاخام هليل ، المعاصر الأقدم ليسوع ،
who, when asked by a pagan
عندما سئل من قبل وثني (لا ديني)
to sum up the whole of Jewish teaching while he stood on one leg,
لتلخيص مجمل التعاليم اليهودية بينما كان واقفا على ساق واحدة،
said, "That which is hateful to you, do not do to your neighbor.
قال، " الشئ المكروه بالنسبة لك، لا تفعله لجارك.
That is the Torah and everything else is only commentary."
تلك هي التوراة وأي شئ آخر هو فقط شروحات."
And the rabbis and the early fathers of the church who said that
وقد قال الحاخامات وبابوات الكنيسة في وقت مبكر
any interpretation of scripture
أن أي تفسير للنصوص المقدسة
that bred hatred and disdain was illegitimate.
يقوم بتوليد الكراهية والازدراء هو غير شرعي.
And we need to revive that spirit.
ونحن بحاجة إلى إحياء تلك الروح.
And it's not just going to happen
وانها ليست مجرد شئ سيحدث
because a spirit of love wafts us down.
لأن روح من نسمات الحب تأتي إلينا.
We have to make this happen,
يجب أن نجعل هذا يتحقق،
and we can do it
ويمكننا فعل ذلك
with the modern communications
مع الإتصالات الحديثة
that TED has introduced.
التي قدمها تيد.
Already I've been tremendously heartened
لقد أُثلج صدري بالفعل
at the response of all our partners.
لكل التجاوب من قبل شركاؤنا.
In Singapore, we have a group
في سينغافورة لدينا مجموعة
going to use the Charter to heal divisions
ستقوم بإستخدام الميثاق لرأب الإنقسامات
recently that have sprung up in Singaporean society,
التي ظهرت مؤخراً في المجتمع السينغافوري،
and some members of the parliament want
ويرغب بعض أعضاء البرلمان
to implement it politically.
تطبيقه سياسياً.
In Malaysia, there is going to be an art exhibition
في ماليزيا سيقام معرض فني
in which leading artists are going to be
الذي سيقوم فيه كبار الفنانين
taking people, young people,
بأخذ الناس، الشباب،
and showing them that compassion also lies
ويشرحوا لهم أن الرحمة أيضاً موجودة
at the root of all art.
في جذور كل الفنون.
Throughout Europe, the Muslim communities
وعبر أوروبا، المجتمعات الإسلامية
are holding events and discussions,
يقيمون مناسبات ونقاشات
are discussing the centrality of compassion
يناقشون مركزية التراحم
in Islam and in all faiths.
في الإسلام وفي كل المعتقدات.
But it can't stop there. It can't stop with the launch.
لكن لا يمكن أن تتوقف هنا. لا يمكن أن تتوقف في الإطلاق.
Religious teaching, this is where we've gone so wrong,
التعليم الديني، ها هنا حيث مضينا بطريقة خاطئة،
concentrating solely on believing abstruse doctrines.
مركزين فقط على صعوبة مذهب الإعتقاد الديني.
Religious teaching must always lead to action.
التعليم الديني يجب أن يؤدي دائماً الى العمل.
And I intend to work on this till my dying day.
وأنا أنوي العمل على هذا حتى مماتي.
And I want to continue with our partners
وأرغب في المواصلة مع شركاؤنا
to do two things --
لفعل أمرين --
educate and stimulate compassionate thinking.
تعليم وتحفيز التفكير التراحمي.
Education because we've so
التعليم لأننا قد تخلينا
dropped out of compassion.
عن التراحم.
People often think it simply means
عادة ما يعتقد الناس أنه يعني ببساطة
feeling sorry for somebody.
الشعور بالأسف لشخص ما.
But of course you don't understand compassion
لكنك بالطبع لا تفهم معنى التراحم
if you're just going to think about it.
اذا كنت تفكر في الأمر هكذا.
You also have to do it.
يجب عليك أن تفعل شئ.
I want them to get the media involved
أرغب في أن يتدخل الإعلام
because the media are crucial
لأن الإعلام له دور حاسم
in helping to dissolve some of the stereotypical views
في المساعدة في حل بعض الآراء النمطية
we have of other people,
التي لدينا عن بقية الناس،
which are dividing us from one another.
التي تفرقنا من بعضنا البعض.
The same applies to educators.
والشئ نفسه ينطبق على المعلمين.
I'd like youth to get a sense of
أرغب في أن يكون للشباب نوع من
the dynamism, the dynamic and challenge
الحيوية ، حيوية و تحدي
of a compassionate lifestyle.
المتمثل في نمط الحياة الوجدانية.
And also see that it demands acute intelligence,
وأيضاً معرفة أن ذلك يتطلب ذكاء حاداً،
not just a gooey feeling.
ليس فقط مشاعر جيدة.
I'd like to call upon scholars to explore
أود أن أدعو العلماء لإستكشاف
the compassionate theme
موضوع الرحمة
in their own and in other people's traditions.
في تقاليدهم وفي تقاليد الناس الآخرين.
And perhaps above all,
وربما فوق كل ذلك،
to encourage a sensitivity about
تشجيع وجود حساسية حول
uncompassionate speaking,
المتحدثين غير الرحماء. (من قادة السياسة والأديان)
so that because people have this Charter,
بحيث يكون لدى الناس هذا الميثاق،
whatever their beliefs or lack of them,
بغض النظر عن معتقداتهم أو عدمه،
they feel empowered
أنهم يشعرون بالقوة
to challenge uncompassionate speech,
لمجابهة الحديث غير الرحيم،
disdainful remarks
مترفعين عن تصريحات
from their religious leaders, their political leaders,
من قادة أديانهم، وقادتهم السياسيين،
from the captains of industry.
من قادة الصناعة.
Because we can change the world,
لأننا نستطيع تغيير العالم،
we have the ability.
لدينا المقدرة.
I would never have thought of putting the Charter online.
لم أفكّر أبداً في وضع الميثاق على الإنترنت
I was still stuck in the old world
كنت ما أزال عالقة في العالم القديم
of a whole bunch of boffins sitting together in a room
لحفنة من العلماء يجلسون معا في غرفة
and issuing yet another arcane statement.
ويقومون بإصدار بيان آخر غامض.
And TED introduced me to a whole new way
ومؤتمر "تيد" قدمني الى طريقة جديدة كلياً
of thinking and presenting ideas.
للتفكير ، وعرض الأفكار.
Because that is what is so wonderful about TED.
لأن ذلك هو الشئ المدهش حول تيد.
In this room, all this expertise,
في هذه القاعة، كل الخبرات،
if we joined it all together,
اذا جمعناها سوياً
we could change the world.
ربما نستطيع تغيير العالم.
And of course the problems sometimes seem insuperable.
وبالطبع تبدو المشاكل في بعض الأحيان مستعصية.
But I'd just like to quote, finish at the end
لكني أريد أن أقتبس، في الختام
with a reference to a British author, an Oxford author
إستناداً على كاتب إنجليزي، مؤلف من أوكسفورد
whom I don't quote very often,
الذي لا أقتبس منه كثيراً،
C.S. Lewis.
سي أس لويس.
But he wrote one thing that stuck in my mind
لكنه كتب شيئاً علق في ذهني
ever since I read it when I was a schoolgirl.
منذ أن قرأته عندما كنت تلميذة في المدرسة.
It's in his book "The Four Loves."
وذلك في كتابه، المحبوبات الأربعة.
He said that he distinguished between erotic love,
لقد قال، أنه ميّز بين الحب الجنسي،
when two people gaze, spellbound, into each other's eyes.
عندما يتبادل شخصين النظر، يدوخون في عيون بعضهما البعض.
And then he compared that to friendship,
ثم قارن ذلك مع الصداقة.
when two people stand side by side, as it were, shoulder to shoulder,
عندما يقف شخصين بجانب أحدها الآخر، كتف بكتف،
with their eyes fixed on a common goal.
مع عيونهم متجهه نحو هدف مشترك.
We don't have to fall in love with each other,
لا يلزمنا الوقوع في حب بعضنا البعض،
but we can become friends.
لكن نستطيع أن نصبح أصدقاء.
And I am convinced.
وأنا على إقتناع.
I felt it very strongly
لقد أحسست بذلك بشدة
during our little deliberations at Vevey,
خلال مداولاتنا في فيفي،
that when people of all different persuasions
أنه عندما يجتمع الناس من مشارب مختلفة معاً
come together, working side by side
ويعملون جنباً الى جنب
for a common goal,
من أجل هدف مشترك،
differences melt away.
تذوب الإختلافات بينهم.
And we learn amity.
ونتعلم نحن المحبة.
And we learn to live together and to get to know one another.
ونتعلم أن نعيش سوياً وأن نعرف بعضنا البعض.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)